Guide to the David Fender Papers TAM.104
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
David Fender Papers
1952-1974
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Fender, David
TAM.104
3 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
U.S. Trotskyist David Fender was active in the Socialist Workers Party and a number of its political factions and offshootsFender was also secretary to Peng Shu-tse and Chen Pi-len in Paris in the 1960s. Peng was one of the founders of the Chinese Communist Party and the leader of the Trotskyist movement in China from the 1920s until the early 1950s when he and his wife, Chen Pi-len, were forced to flee the country. The collection contains Fender's correspondence with numerous Trotskyists and other leftists, including correspondence and interviews with exiled Chinese Trotskyist leaders Peng Shu-tse and Chen Pi-len. There are also manuscripts and articles, internal discussion materials from the Fourth International, internal documents and printed ephemera from various Trotskyist organizations, and audiotapes of meetings and other events of various U.S. Trotskyist organizations, including a talk by James P. Cannon.
Box 1-3
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I, Correspondence; II, Manuscipts and Articles; III, Fourth International; IV, Trotskyist Organizations; V. Audiotapes.
Historical/Biographical Note
U.S. Trotskyist David Fender was active in the Socialist Workers Party and a number of its political factions and offshoots; mainly the Communist Tendency, the Leninist Faction (later known as the Class Struggle League), the Vanguard Newsletter and the Spartacist League. Fender was also secretary to Peng Shu-tse and Chen Pi-len in Paris in the 1960s. Peng was one of the founders of the Chinese Communist Party and the leader of the Trotskyist movement in China from the 1920s until the early 1950s when he and his wife, Chen Pi-len, also an active Trotskyist, were forced to flee the country with many of their followers after Mao Zedong's attack on the Chinese Trotskyists.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains Fender's correspondence with numerous Trotskyists and other leftists, including correspondence and interviews with exiled Chinese Trotskyist leaders Peng Shu-tse and Chen Pi-len. There are also manuscripts and articles, internal discussion materials from the Fourth International [serials to be removed and placed in the Library's serial collection], internal documents and printed ephemera from various Trotskyist organizations, and audiotapes of meetings and other events of various U.S. Trotskyist organizations, including a talk by James P. Cannon [separated to the Library's Oral History collection].
NOTE: There is a folder level (paper) inventory available at the Library. Please direct further inquiries to: tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by David Fender, 1978. The accession number associated with this gift is 1977.002.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Neil Sih Typescript: "Five Years of the Left Opposition in China: An Attempt to Explain Its Failure to Make Progress" (Tamiment 303)
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Trotskyism |z China.; Trotskyism |z United States.; Trotskyism.; Communism -- China.; Communist parties |z United States.; Communism.; Communism -- United States.; Socialist Workers Party; Peng, Shu-tse, 1895-; Chen, Pi-len; Class Struggle League; Fender, David; Fourth International; Fender, David
- Correspondence, 1959-1974 (Box 1)
  - Charles Adams, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alan, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mick Barry, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John Barzman, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Terry W. Bell, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Nick Benjamin (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jim Bingham, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - David Buckholder, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - John Connolly, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - James P. Cannon, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clive, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - M.C. Cook, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - David Cunningham, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Daisy, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - G. de Leon (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Marie Fraince de Deumat (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ed di Tullio, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Ed di Tullio, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hal Draper, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fred Ferguson, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Kevin Fitzpatrick, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Flour Gilbert, July 23, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Earl Gilman, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Barbara Gregorich, 1968-1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Neal Grover, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Joe and Reba Hansen, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Jim Hays, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Sam Hunt, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Jan, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Fred Joffe (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Michael Kappes, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Malcolm Kaufman, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - John Keeley, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Chris [Kinder?], 1971 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Gerard Lebrun, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ralph Levitt, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Peter Manti, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Bill Moore, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Elliot Moore, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - David Morgan, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 39a)
  - George Novack, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Laurens Otter (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Peter Peterson, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Henry Platsky, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Bill Ramseyer (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Al Richardson, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Harold Robins, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - James Robertson, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Franklin Rosemont, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Simone (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Socialist Workers Party, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Ronnie Somerlott and Ted Campbell, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Kathleen L.B. Steward, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Judy Stuart, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Peter, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Ernest Tate, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Thorsten Thalstein, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - David Thorstad, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Time/Life 1968 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - M. Torigian, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Mike Torney, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Harry Turner, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Harry Turner, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Keith and Valerie Veness, 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Albert Weisbord, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Peng Shu-tse and Chen Pi-len, 1952-1969 (Box 1)
  - Material by and about Peng and Chen, 1952-1969 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Correspondence of Chen and Peng with D.F., 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Interview with Chen-August 12, 1966 and February 10, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Correspondence with Yamanishe and Nakajama, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Interview with Peng by D.F., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Peng's report on trip to Japan, November 5, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Correspondence and statements by Peng, 1950 and 1960 (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Manuscripts and Articles, 1936-1972 (Box 2)
  - Bishop, Hillman M., "The American League Against War and Fascism 1936" (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chuo, Chien, "New Development of the 'Cultural Revolution'" (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cunningham, David, "On Political Differences-an Elementary Clarification on What Politics Means" (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dicken, N. "Genesis of Pabloism and Exodus from Pseudo-Trotskyist Fraud" (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Farien, Antonio, "Mao's Purge and the Working Class", April 20, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fender, David, manuscripts and notes (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gilman, Earl, "Open Letter to the P.O.R.", January 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Declaration of the I.S. of the Fourth International on the First Cosmic Flight, April 12, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hardie, K., "The Labour Party and Our Tactics in Britain", 1970s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Hays, Jim, "The International Committee and Left Pabloism"; "Centrism or Permanent Revolution" (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Jones, David, position papers on the I.S. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Platsky, Henry, "Countermotion on Current Organizational Matters and the Fusion with C.S.L." (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Proletarian Military Policy (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Saling, Rick, "The Trouble with Liz...", February 17, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Turner, Harry, "Memo on 'Maosim Run Amok'"; "Amendments to 'Marxism vs S.W.P.'" (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Fourth International-Internal Discussion, 1940-1969 (Box 2)
  - F.I.-Conference of I.K.D., R.C.L. and S.L. in London, November 23-November 24 1940 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Internal Discussion within F.I., 1940s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Internal Discussion within F.I., 1952-1969 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Internal Discussion within F.I., 1954-1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Internal Discussion within F.I., 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Internal Discussion within F.I., 1967-1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Documents on Reunification, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - F.I.-Internal Discussion on Japan, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Internal Debate in French Section of F.I., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Organizations, 1947-1979 (Box 3)
  - Black Workers Congress (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Chicago Surrealist Group, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Class Struggle League, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Committee for a Rank and File Caucus, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Communications Workers of America, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Communist Tendency-agendas and minutes, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Communist Tendency, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Freedon Socialist Party, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - International Marxist Group, Britain, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - International Socialists, August 1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Jeunesse Communiste Revolutionnaire (J.C.R., F.I. youth section P.C.I.), 1960s (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - J.C.R. and P.C.I leaflets and statements re: uprising, May 1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Leninist Faction, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Ligue Communiste (until 1968 called Partido Communiste Internationaliste), 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - National Caucus of Labor Committees (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - New York Revolutionary Committee (NYRC), 1972 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Organizaing Committee for Workers' Councils (OCWC), 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Proletarian Party, United States of America, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Rank and File Trade Union Caucus, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Revolutionary Communist Party of Britain, 1947-1949 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Revolutionary Workers Group, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Socialist Chartist (Britain), 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Socialist Forum, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Socialist Labor League of Britain, June 1960 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Socialist Reconstruction, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Socialist Workers Party-convention material, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Socialist Workers Party-national office, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - New York Spartacist Committee-minutes, November 1964-January 1967 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Spartacist League-Political Bureau Minutes, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Spartacist League, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Spartacus (Germany), 1969-1973 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Vanguard Newsletter correspondence and statements, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Vanguard Newsletter-Bay Area minutes, December 21, 1972 and January 2, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Vanguard Newsletter-New york City minutes, August 1972-February 1973 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Vanguard Newsletter mailing labels (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Young Socialist Alliance, 1966-1972 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Documents on Israel (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous Political Statements and Leaflets, 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Foreign Bulletins, 1962-1969 (Box 3, Folder 39)